Guide to the Association of Professors and Researchers in Religious Education Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Association of Professors and Researchers in Religious Education Records
1963-1998
RG 154
Yale University Divinity School Library
6
(13 boxes)
Correspondence and organizational records document the work of the Association of Professors and Researchers in Religious Education and its predecessor organization from 1963 to 1995. The Association of Professors and Researchers in Religious Education grew out of the Professors and Research Section of the Division of Christian Education of the National Council of Churches. The group decided to move in the direction of a separate autonomous society that would become more ecumenical and interfaith.
Association of Professors and Researchers in Religious Education
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited by the APRRE.
Biographical / Historical
The Association of Professors and Researchers in Religious Education (APRRE) grew out of the Professors and Research Section of the Division of Christian Education of the National Council of Churches. For an account of the early history of the Section, see the Paper in Box 1, Folder1 that was presented at the 1963 meeting by Paul H. Vieth, Horace Bushnell Professor of Christian Nurture at Yale University Divinity School. For a more complete history of APRRE, see the essay in Box 2, Folder 14, which was written by Donald F. Williams, Executive Secretary, 1970-1990.
In 1969 the Professors and Research Section decided to meet independently of the National Council of Churches, and its last meeting was held February 6-8, 1970 in St. Louis. The group decided to move in the direction of a separate autonomous society that would become more ecumenical and interfaith. Instead of staying with the predominantly Protestant, interdenominational Council, they wanted to reach out to Roman Catholic, Jewish, and other educators. Their goals were to be: scholarly in focus, international in scope, collegial in structure, and inclusive in stance.
Donald Williams suggested a name for the new organization, Association of Professors and Researchers in Religious Education, in a Feb. 18, 1970 letter to Allen J. Moore. Plans were made for the inaugural meeting on Oct. 23-25, 1970 at the Statler Hilton in New York city, at the same time that other scholarly societies in the field of religion were meeting. About 34 persons attended one or more of the sessions. The officers elected in February continued for another year: Allen J. Moore, President; Neely D. McCarter, President-Elect; Harriet L. Miller, Treasurer; and Donald F. Williams, Secretary.
The purpose of APRRE was to provide scholars in the field of religious education with a forum for the interchange of ideas and projects and the mutual support for their research and teaching. Instead of a Constitution or By Laws, the group decided to be guided by a statement of principles and structures, which was written in 1971 by Neely McCarter. This grew into a set of "Operating Policies and Practices," which was adopted in 1974 and revised in 1991. Also in 1971, a newsletter was published for the first time; it was edited by the Executive Secretary and featured announcements of the annual meetings and news of the scholarly work and activity of its members.
Since 1971 APRRE has worked very closely with the Religious Education Association of the U.S. and Canada. A meeting in Washington, DC, in June 1971 was attended by representatvies of both groups and it set the stage for a number of cooperative ventures. Many APRRE annual meetings were held in tandem with those of the REA. APRRE representatives sat on the REA Editorial Committee, and papers from the annual meetings were often published in the journal Religious Education. The March/ April 1980 issue was devoted to APRRE papers, and later that year it was decided to make the journal a joint publication of the two organizations. Randolph Crump Miller, editor of the journal for twenty years, was an active member of APRRE; he was Professor of Religious Education at Yale Divinity School and followed Paul Vieth as the Horace Bushnell Professor of Christian Nurture.
Since 1976 APRRE has been a full constituent member of the Council of Societies for the Study of Religion, and announcements of APRRE meetings and activities were published in the CSSR Bulletin. Some meetings were held in conjunction with the Society for the Scientific Study of Religion and the Religious Research Association, and occasionally with the American Academy of Religion and Society of Biblical Literature. Abstracts were published with the papers presented at these joint meetings. In addition, APRRE was a charter member of the National Council on Religion and Public Education, and sent delegates to their meetings.
Ever since 1970 annual meetings of APRRE have been held in major cities of the U.S. and Canada. Programs have been planned each year by the President-Elect, with help of a number of colleagues. A Call for Papers was issued at the beginning of each year and decisions were made regarding a theme and schedule. Ellis Nelson began the practice of a formal Presidential Address at the 1973 annual meeting. Task forces were introduced in 1973-74 and the popular Breakfast Roundtables were started in 1973. Other features were added through the years, such as Research Interest Groups, denominational assemblies, gender groupings for breakfast or lunch, liturgies, Doctoral Student Recognition presentations, and formal tributes recognizing the retirement or death of members. Travel grants were initiated in 1975 and they were enhanced by a capital funds campaign. Scholarship assistance was offered to a number of graduate students so that they could attend the annual meetings.
With a grant from the Lilly Endowment, APRRE held a consultation on revitalizing itself on July 15-16 at Garrett-Evangelical Theological Seminary. Concerns had been expressed regarding the identity and purpose of the association, as well as its relationship to the REA and other organizations. In 1995 APRRE celebrated its 25th anniversary in Chicago. A banquet honored all the past presidents and a special booklet was published for the occasion. Over 150 persons were in attendance.
Donal F. Williams served as Executive Secreatry from 1970 to 1990. The year 1990-1991 was a transition year, with Clarisse Croteau-Chonka and Burton Everist serving in the interim. Padraic O'Hare was called to a three-year term for the period 1991 to 1994, and he was followed by Charles F. Melchert.
Scope and Contents
I. Pre-APRRE
II. History, Organization and Policy of APRRE
III. Committee Records
IV. Secretarial Files
V. Annual Meetings
VI. Publications
VII. Membership
The material dates from 1963 (pre-APRRE) to 1995, with a few documents from the years 1996-1998. Current records of APRRE are in the possession of the Executive Secretary (In 1998: Charles F. Melchert, Lancaster Theological Seminary, Lancaster, PA)
The largest portions of the documentation relate to the correspondence of one Executive Secretary, Donald F. Williams, (1970-1990) and the programs of the APRRE annual meetings. Closely associated with the APRRE during all its years of operation was the Religious Education Association of the U. S. and Canada, which had its executive offices at Yale Divinity School from 1973 to 1984 and its editorial and membership offices for a much longer period. The REA archives constitute Record Group No. 74 at the Yale Divinity School Library. The files of the National Council on Religion and Public Education have been placed in YDSL Record Group No. 34.
Other records at the Yale Divinity School Library also complement the archives of the APRRE, especiallly the personal papers of Paul H. Vieth and Randolph Crump Miller. Another APRRE leader who was on the faculty at YDS from several years was Iris V. Cully. Graduates of Yale University who were prominent in the life, work, and correspondence of APRRE include John H. Peatling, David S. Steward, Charles F. Melchert, Sara Little, Neely McCarter, and William B. Kennedy. Other Yale graduates identified in the records are Boardman W. Kathan, REA General Secretary 1970-1982, and Kenneth Stokes, director of the REA Faith Development in the Adult Life Cycle Prjoect.
Series I includes some records of the last years of the Professors and Research Section before it becamse independent and re-constituted itself as APRRE.
Series II is a miscellaneous collection of files related to the history, structure, organization, and policy of APRRE. Included are documents pertaining to a membership questionnaire, travel grant development, endowment fundraising, and two external policyi issues, the 1971 "Prayer Amendment" before the U.S. Congress, and the Marianne Sawicki case in 1989. Also included are the records of the 1994 Revitalization Conference, which dealt with the identity of the organization and relationships with the REA and other groups.
Series III contains the records of the Executive Committee, arranged chronologically, and the records of various other ad hoc committees and task forces. Also included are the records of the very active Doctoral Student Recognition Committee, which began in 1989.
Series IV consists of the Secretarial Files. The files of the Donald F. Williams era are in two parts: 1) General Correspondence, arranged alphabeticaly by name or organization, and 2) Administrative Files, dealing with membership promotion and annual meeting hotels. These are followed by a single file for the transition year of 1990-1991 with Clarisse Croteau-Chonka and Burton Everist, and the files of Padraic O'Hare (1991-1994) and Charles F. Melchert (1994- ).
The voluminous files of the Annual Meetings, Series V, are arranged chronologically. For the most part, programs, annual business meetings, and financial reports have been kept together. Occasional Abstracts of papers are included in separate files, but there has been no attempt made to include the complete text of the many papers that were presented, except for some Presidential Addresses and the winning Doctoral Student Recognition essays.
Series VI, Publications, consists of the biennial newsletters that were started in 1971, and the Proceedings that were gathered and published for the first time in 1997. Copies of related journals, such as Religious Education and Religion and Public Education are in the library's cataloged collection, and publications of the Council of Societies for the Study of Religion are also cataloged elsewhere.
Series VII contains the membership lists, directories, and mailing lists of APRRE, arranged in chronological order.
Arrangement
I. Pre-APRRE
II. History, Organization and Policy of APRRE
III. Committee Records
IV. Secretarial Files
V. Annual Meetings
VI. Publications
VII. Membership
Religious education; Religious Education Association
- Pre-APRRE: Professors and Research Section, NCCUSA, Series I
  - A history, "The Professors and Research Association Section" by Paul H. Vieth (1922-1963) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - By Laws and Organization, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee, 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Ad Hoc committees (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Secretarial files (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Membership (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mailing lists (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual meeting programs (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual meeting papers, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
- History, Organization, and Policy of APRRE, Series II
  - History and structure (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Officers, Executive Committee members, 1970- (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Operating policies and practices, 1971,1974, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Articles of Organization, Massachusetts, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Job description, Executive Secretary, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Membership questionnaire, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Travel grant endowment (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Travel grant questionnaire (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Endowment fundraising (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Revitalization Conference, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
  - "Prayer Amendment" issue, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Marianne Sawicki case, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Committee Records, Series III
  - Executive Committee
    - Records, 1970-1998 (Box 3, Folder 27-52)
  - Other committees
    - Nominating Committee (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Task Force on Membership, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Task Force on Special Interest Groups, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Search Committee, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Doctoral Student Recognition Committee
    - Records, 1989-1998 (Box 4, Folder 58-62)
- Secretarial Files, Series IV
  - Williams era (1970-1990)
    - A (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Association of Theological Schools (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - B (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Barber, Lucie (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - Browning, Robert (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - Bryce, Mary Charles (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - C (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - Cully, Iris V. (Box 5, Folder 70)
    - Council on the Study of Religion, 1973-1985 (Box 5, Folder 71-80)
    - Council of Societies for the Study of Religion, 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - D (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - E (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - F (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - G (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - H (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - I - J (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - K (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - Kennedy, William B. (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - L (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Little, Sara (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - M (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - McCarter, Neely (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - McConnell, Taylor (Box 6, Folder 94)
    - Marthaler, Berard (Box 6, Folder 95)
    - Moore, Allen J. (Box 6, Folder 96)
    - N (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - Nelson, C. Ellis (Box 6, Folder 98)
    - National Association of Professors of Christian Education (Box 6, Folder 99)
    - National Council on Religion and Public Education (Box 6, Folder 100)
    - O (Box 6, Folder 101)
    - P - Q (Box 7, Folder 102)
    - Peating, John H. (Box 7, Folder 103)
    - R (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - Religious Education Association (Boardman W. Kathan), 1970-1982 (Box 7, Folder 105-106)
    - Religious Education Association (Kenneth Stokes), 1982-1984 (Box 7, Folder 107)
    - Religious Education Association (Randolph C. Miller, Dorothy Savage, Donald Russo), 1982-1990 (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - REA Faith Development in the Adult Life Cycle Project (Kenneth Stokes) (Box 7, Folder 109)
    - S (Box 7, Folder 110)
    - Slusser, Gerald H. (Box 7, Folder 111)
    - Sparkman, G. Temp (Box 7, Folder 112)
    - Steward, David S. (Box 7, Folder 113)
    - Society for the Scientific Study of Religion, 1970-1989 (Box 7, Folder 114-115)
    - T (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - Thompson, Norma H. (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - U -V (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - W (Box 8, Folder 119)
    - Webster, Margaret (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - X - Z (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - Administrative files - Membership promotion (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Administrative files - Annual meeting hotels (Box 8, Folder 123)
  - Croteau-Chonka / Everist era (1990-1991)
    - General files (Box 8, Folder 124)
  - O'Hare era
    - General files, 1991-1994 (Box 8, Folder 125-128)
  - Melchert era (1994- )
    - General files, 1994-1995 (Box 8, Folder 129)
- Annual Meetings, 1970; Series V
  - 1st, New York City, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 130)
  - 2nd, Chicago, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 131)
  - 3rd, Boston, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 132)
  - 3rd annual meeting abstracts, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 133)
  - 4th, Toronto, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 134)
  - 5th, Washington DC, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 135)
  - 6th, Philadelphia, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 136)
  - 7th, Philadelphia, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 137)
  - 7th annual meeting abstracts, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 138)
  - 8th, St. Louis, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 139)
  - 9th, Hartford, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 140)
  - 9th annual meeting abstracts, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 141)
  - 10th, Toronto, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 142)
  - 11th, Cincinnati, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 143)
  - 11th annual meeting abstracts, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 144)
  - 12th, East Lansing, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 145)
  - 13th, Providence, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 146)
  - 13th annual meeting abstracts, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 147)
  - 14th, Anaheim, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 148)
  - 15th, Chicago, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 149)
  - 15th annual meeting abstracts, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 150)
  - 15th annual meeting registration, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 151)
  - 16th, Chicago, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 152)
  - 17th, Washington DC, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 153)
  - 17th annual meeting abstracts, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 154)
  - 18th, Toronto, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 155)
  - 19th, Chicago, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 156)
  - 20th, New York City, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 157)
  - 20th annual business meeting, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 158)
  - 20th annual meeting: Union Theological Seminary/ Teachers College luncheon, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 159)
  - 20th annual meeting papers: History of Union Theological Seminary, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 160)
  - Doctoral Student Recognition winning essay, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 161)
  - 21st, Boulder, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 162)
  - 21st annual business meeting, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 163)
  - 22nd, Chicago, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 164)
  - 22nd annual business meeting, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 165)
  - Doctoral Student Recognition winning essay, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 166)
  - 23rd, Indianapolis, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 167)
  - 23rd annual business meeting, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 168)
  - 24th, Fort Worth, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 169)
  - Doctoral Student Recognition winning essay, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 170)
  - 25th, Chicago, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 171)
  - Doctoral Student Recognition winning essay, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 172)
  - 26th, Chicago (25th anniversary), 1995 (Box 11, Folder 173)
  - Doctoral Student Recognition winning essay, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 174)
  - 27th, New Orleans, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 175)
  - 28th, Oakland, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 176)
  - Doctoral Student Recognition winning essay, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 177)
- Publications, Series VI
  - APRRE Newsletters, 1971-1998 (Box 12, Folder 178-186)
  - Proceedings, Annual meeting, 1997 (Box 12, Folder 187)
- Membership, Series VII
  - Membership lists, 1970-1977 (Box 13, Folder 188-189)
  - Membership directories, 1978-1988 (Box 13, Folder 190-192)
  - Mailing list, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 193)
  - Membership directories, 1991-1998 (Box 13, Folder 194-196)